[music]
>> 1968 it [music] was one of those years
at least for me that I knew it was an
important year when I was in it.
>> Born to be wild was the '68 anthem. It's
all about the new freedom and if there's
an element of danger to it. And it was
by Steppenwolf and Steppenwolf was the
Herman Hesse novel that everyone was
reading.
>> It was great in those days you could
turn on the radio and just hear great
music just at a flick of a dial.
>> The joining of the students with the all
powerful unions changed French society
there and then almost overnight.
The country stopped working.
>> [music]
>> It was this exciting moment when people
said, "This is the America we want. This
is the president we want."
>> [music]
>> It was the year that Martin Luther King
and Robert Kennedy were assassinated.
>> [music]
>> This was a real moment where Europeans
in general wow, this is really intense
what's happening in America.
>> [music]
>> Even when you're a young kid you kind of
know this is a pivotal year.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The stars of 1968 brought new and
unexplored worlds into [music] people's
homes with the debut of Jacques
Cousteau's The Undersea World. This was
a lyrical contrast to how the year would
unfold.
>> Today we begin one of our most important
assignments.
To trace the migrations of various shark
species.
>> The Undersea World of Jacques Cousteau
was
the thing that introduced [music]
everyone to this incredible underwater
life.
>> This documentary really changed a lot of
the ideas about documentaries because we
could actually go underneath [music]
the water.
>> It felt quite psychedelic.
I don't think that was the intention as
such, but it felt like it was all part
of this incredible decade. You know, a
sort of decade of discovery [music] I
suppose.
>> When they weren't under the sea looking
at fabulous fish, they were on the yacht
and they were drinking wine and eating
baguettes. And so you see the beginning
of falling in love [music] with French
culture.
>> There was an awful lot of red wine being
drunk. And best of all, there was
Jacques Cousteau's son, Philippe. He
would often be found playing an acoustic
guitar in as Gallic [music]
a manner as you could possibly imagine.
>> Really in [music] 1968 it was a fun
time, it was an exciting time, but
yachts really weren't that popular. But
after this fantastic series,
>> [music]
>> people wanted a yacht and that's what
the super rich started buying.
>> New forms of subversive comedy were also
being explored on American television.
>> Hi, Big Dick here.
>> Rowan and Martin's Laugh-In. Now, that
was a comedy sketch [music] show.
We never heard of these two comics.
These guys were making jokes off each
other except
the notch up was Goldie Hawn. She was
just
uh bonkers.
>> Dan Rowan, I'd like you to be Goldie
Hawn.
>> No, no, no.
I met you before. You remember?
>> I know.
>> I felt watching it
that the counterculture had started to
infect
mainstream America. Even Richard Nixon
realized the the positive aspects of
appearing on
>> Sock it to me. Sock it to me. Sock it to
me. Sock it to me.
>> Sock it to yourself.
>> Sock it to me?
>> Obviously being Richard Nixon, he wasn't
[music] particularly hilarious. But the
notion of Richard Nixon saying, "Sock it
to me."
was almost unheard of.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> January of 1968 also saw the Tet
Offensive
of the war.
>> The Tet Offensive was launched by the
Viet Cong to coincide with Tet, which
was the Vietnamese New Year.
>> I mean, this goes back for years, for
centuries. This is the time when you
have an offensive. Americans had [music]
no idea.
>> The idea of the the Tet Offensive
[music] was to put 67,000
troops, and not just go for the
countryside where they were strong, but
attack provincial capitals and major
cities such as Saigon.
Now, Saigon, of course, was where the
bulk of the American press was
stationed. It was the first time that
the Vietnamese war had come to the
press.
>> It was in our living room at 6:30 and
6:00 every evening. We began to see that
war was a complicated thing. We started
to see that maybe we were the bad guys
here. And
being an American, that was a weird
place to be.
>> The most pivotal moment in [music] the
American perception of the Vietnam War
came when Walter Cronkite said on CBS,
"We're not going to win this war."
>> Walter Cronkite was so revered and
trusted and, you know, just this sort of
father figure for so many Americans that
to hear this coming from [music] him
uh really rattled everything.
>> Almost overnight, you see perceptions
changing. You see people saying, "Bring
our boys back home. It's [music] not
going to work. We have to get out of
these overseas wars."
>> [music]
[music]
[singing]
>> "Walk Away Renee" by The Four Tops has
got the wonderful vocal talents of Levi
Stubbs. And you've got this great spirit
of the song. It's a kind of haunting uh
brokenhearted ballad with this very rich
production.
>> In many ways, they were uh
groundbreaking. Levi Stubbs [music] was
starting to mix bits of Bob Dylan's art
in the way he sang [music] into soul.
So, to have a black man actually sing
this way was quite revolutionary.
>> In America, the Civil Rights Movement
was reaching a climax with the Memphis
Sanitation Strike.
>> In February, sanitation workers in
Memphis, a pretty tough and difficult
job,
>> [music]
>> they realized they were being paid much
less than their white counterparts. So,
they took the [music] decision to go out
on strike.
>> Black men were called boy. That was just
routine. So, to stand up and make a sign
that said, "I am a man"
was a provocation,
a statement, a stance of immense
importance and power. Because then, they
could have been arrested for civil
disorder. If they'd gone into jail in
Memphis, Tennessee, who knows what would
have happened [music] to them. They
wouldn't have gotten any justice, that's
for sure.
>> It was all about say saying I'm a man,
I'm you know, I should be treated as
one. [music] And so that's where it came
from and it was it manifested in a big
movement and it became a student
movement and uh you know, it it became a
a sort of national concern.
>> [music]
[cheering]
[music]
>> I am announcing today my candidacy
for the presidency of the United States.
>> In the spring of 1968, Robert Kennedy
entered the race for president and that
was a thrilling moment. Lyndon Johnson
had stood down. He said he wasn't going
to run. Lyndon unfortunately was between
him and the old world, but Bobby was
young and new and young people loved
him.
>> For me growing up as as a black girl,
the Kennedy name had all that magic. JFK
had done a lot to help, especially and
Bobby especially, had done a lot to help
Martin Luther King.
>> He was really saying extraordinarily
clear-eyed progressive things in that
campaign.
>> It was [music] this exciting moment when
people said, "This is the America we
want. This is the president we want."
[music] And he's forward-looking and
it's about rights and it's also about
getting out of the war.
>> The Biches, a film by Claude Chabrol,
was part of the the French New Wave,
which also [music] featured Godard and
Truffaut. On the surface, it was a film
about a lesbian relationship, but in
fact, it was meant to represent [music]
a lot of the political undertones of
what were going on at the time,
particularly in [music] France, too. It
was about power. It was about buying
people, and it was about manipulation.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Mighty Quinn, that was a fascinating
process.
I think Albert Grossman, Dylan's
manager, was frustrated [music] because
Dylan had hurt himself in a motorcycle
accident, and he wasn't working. He
wasn't touring.
There's no income.
Hey Bob, give me some songs. Let me sell
some songs.
And [music] this
demo, this
LP
arrived at Feldman's Music in Charing
Cross Road.
>> [music]
>> Everybody was [music] queuing up to hear
the Dylan demo.
And out of that demo came Manfred Mann,
Mighty Quinn. Oh, I mean, they were such
great songs.
And such I mean, it was just amazing
thing.
You know, when you hadn't heard any new
Dylan for so long, and all of a sudden,
boom.
>> [music]
>> 22nd of March, 1968, were the first
rumblings of what would then become the
famous May '68 Paris riots.
>> The Paris University of Nanterre, this
is in the suburbs, and [music] some very
far left groups, they decided to have a
meeting, and a lot of students
participated in that. And there were two
things they were looking at. Number one,
it's discrimination in French society,
which is rife. And number two, it's also
the political bureaucracy that controls
the university and its [music] funding.
It's felt to be incredibly unfair. And
it's a peaceful meeting, it's a
discussion meeting, but unfortunately,
the university authorities cracked down
too hard.
>> When they they sent the police in
>> [music]
>> to break up these rather cross students.
Then, there was in response a
demonstration. This took place on the
22nd of March.
>> It became known as the movement of 22nd
of March, and it was
>> [music]
>> the beginnings of the student uprisings
in Paris.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Open the pod bay doors, Hal.
>> [music]
>> I'm sorry, Dave.
I'm afraid I can't do that.
>> 2001: A Space Odyssey [music] was
Stanley Kubrick's version of the Arthur
C. Clarke novella,
>> [music]
>> and it was a quite an incomprehensible
film, I think it's fair to say.
>> It's such a strange film, and it's such
an unusual blockbuster. You know, you've
got this three-part film, which is about
the birth of man, and then the ascent of
man in space, and then this kind of
heavenly sequence at the end.
>> [music]
>> It was profound because of the music,
the cinematography, and the threat that
our machines were becoming bigger than
us.
>> Rudi Dutschke had been named public
enemy by the Springer press
organization. [music]
Outraged students demonstrated in
defense outside the building. This grew
into a huge revolt against the German
[music] government.
>> Sitting in the morning sun,
I'll be sitting [music]
>> At the start of April, civil rights
leader Martin Luther King visited
Memphis [music]
to lend support to the striking
sanitation workers.
>> On April the 3rd, he made his famous
I've been to the mountaintop speech,
which was saying that if I have to die,
you know, he said that everyone wants
longevity in life, but if I have to die
because of speaking out, then I know
that I've seen a better tomorrow.
Really beautiful, powerful speech.
>> Because I've been to the mountain top.
And I've
seen the promised land.
I may not get there with you.
But I want YOU TO KNOW TONIGHT
THAT WE AS A PEOPLE WILL GET TO THE
PROMISED LAND.
>> And on April the 4th, on the walkway
outside his room, Martin Luther [music]
King was shot by James Earl Ray.
>> [singing]
>> This was, I think, a real moment where
Brit- the British and America and
Europeans in general
went, "Wow,
this is really
intense what's happening in America."
>> I had a transistor radio that I carried
around all the time,
>> [music]
>> and it came across on the radio that he
had been assassinated.
I I you know, it's not possible to
describe what it was like. Uh Bobby
Kennedy uh
had to announce it to [music] a uh
group of black people who had come to
hear him speak. He gave them that
announcement. I remember the way they
sounded when he told them.
>> I have some very sad news for all of
you.
And that is that
Martin Luther King was shot and was
killed tonight in Memphis, Tennessee.
>> [cheering]
>> When Martin Luther King died,
unsurprisingly, there were riots in
cities across America.
And James Brown was booked to play the
Boston Garden, and there's a lot of talk
about whether he should go on, and he
decided that he should. And actually, it
became a kind of peacekeeping mission.
>> James Brown, sensing the moment,
realizing that people were watching on
television rather than going out
rioting, he calmed the situation down.
>> Get your brother down and let us DO THE
SHOW TOGETHER. WE'RE BLACK. DON'T MAKE
US ALL LOOK BAD. Let me finish doing the
show.
>> The result of this
was that there was less crime in Boston
than on a standard Saturday evening.
People had actually stayed at home to
watch James Brown.
>> [music]
>> All right, this is really nice.
>> May '68, the Paris riots. This was a
turning point, not just in student
relations, but in French culture. It was
so big that de Gaulle actually secretly
left the country for a while.
>> After the University of Nanterre is
closed, the closure spread, and by this
point the Sorbonne is closed, and the
students are furious. The students
protest the closure of the Sorbonne.
20,000 of them are outside along with
lecturers and supporters, and the the
demonstration is very badly handled.
>> [music]
[cheering]
>> There starts to be a lot of support for
the student public opinion, trade
unions, other workers, and there was a
one-day strike called, a general strike
[music] called in support of the
students. And on that day, 1 million
people marched through Paris in support
[music] of the students.
>> The joining of the student with the
all-powerful unions changed French
society there and then, almost
overnight.
The country stopped working.
>> France at that moment began to think,
are we going to have another revolution?
Because the French don't do moderation,
they do revolution, and it really looked
like it was about to happen. There was a
great iconic picture of a young woman on
the shoulders of one of the young
protesters. So, it gave the whole world
the idea that maybe there's going to be
another revolution in France, and it
really actually began to look like that.
>> Hello,
>> [music]
>> I love you. Won't you tell me your name?
Hello, I love you. Let me jump in
[music] your game.
Hello, I love you. Won't you tell me
your name?
Hello, I love you. Let me jump [music]
in your game.
She's walking down the street.
Blind to me.
>> "Hello, I love you" is The Doors at
their most pop. It's It's an amazing pop
song, but you know, because Jim Morrison
was a former [music] film studies
student and you know, an arty guy,
you've got some kind of rather
dissonant, slightly [music] odd feel
about it. It's like, you know, saying
"Hello, I love you" instantly, it's kind
of something that's a bit off.
>> Can't think of The Doors without
thinking of my great friend Paul
Rothchild, [music]
who produced those records. To me, the
sound was just great.
Paul did such a great job, and I never
[music] got tired of listening to his
records. Just something about
the combination of that dark
edge to Morrison's voice
and sort of moodiness of the you know,
Paul just captured that so well.
>> [music]
>> Tragedy would strike American [music]
politics once again with the
assassination of presidential hopeful
Bobby Kennedy on June 6th.
>> On June the 5th, Bobby [music] Kennedy
had just won the California primary. An
amazing moment because California is
such an important state in terms of the
presidential [music] election, and
pretty much that would secure him as the
Democratic candidate. And so, he gives
this huge victory speech at the
Ambassador Hotel in Los Angeles.
>> I thank to all of you, and I'm happy to
be with you tonight.
After he's finished his speech, his onto
us decides the way to avoid the crowd is
to take him through the hotel kitchens,
even though his bodyguard is very
dubious about this as he doesn't think
it's a good idea.
>> As he's going through the pantry, "See
your hands, see your hands." A young
Palestinian was in the pantry,
uh came out from behind a rack and
fired.
Shot him once in the head, twice in the
back. He never regained [music]
consciousness. He died early in the
morning.
>> Why he shot him? There's a lot of
theories. This was at the time [music]
when Robert Kennedy wants to pull out of
Vietnam.
Hoover hated him. He was extremely
unpopular. Kennedy, of course, was a
great supporter of Martin Luther King.
He'd also been assassinated.
So, the whole thing [music] is is uh is
a very shady and unpleasant uh chapter
in American [music] history.
>> The effects of it were almost like a
tidal wave [music] across American
politics. And of course, the the
ultimate result of this was that the the
Democratic candidate for president would
be Hubert Humphrey.
>> Bobby Kennedy was going to bring in new
values. He was going to bring in change.
He was charismatic. He was exciting. He
was [music] a revolutionary and he was
going to be president and there are a
lot of people who didn't want that.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Aphrodite's Child was a Greek band. They
had the young Demis Roussos and Vangelis
and they were part of the whole '68
>> [music]
>> uh mood because they were escaping uh
the the military in Greece.
And they traveled to France. They're on
their way to England.
>> And because Paris wasn't functioning,
they couldn't get visas to go further on
to Britain, so they stayed in Paris.
>> [music]
>> In Paris, they recorded this beautiful
song, Rain and Tears, and it was
heartbreaking.
Lovely. And it [music] stayed at number
one in France for 14 weeks.
>> [singing]
[music]
[singing]
>> Support for Alexander Dubček, first
secretary of the Communist Party,
gathered momentum from the Prague
Spring.
>> [music]
>> Dubček's regime, it called it socialism
with a human face. But what it really
meant was slightly liberalizing
>> [music]
>> some of the regime's more extreme
policies.
>> He's talking about freedom of the press.
He's talking about freedom of speech,
the possibility of multiple parties,
importance of economic goods,
consumerism. [music]
And to Moscow, this is rebellion. The
Soviet Union get very concerned. They
start to move their tanks closer to
Czechoslovakia, and they make [music]
the Warsaw Pact, in which pretty much
they agree that if they start to see
anti-communism going on, plurality of
government, too much freedom, they will
agree together to intervene in that
country.
>> Dubček was always loyal to the Soviet
Union. He believed that they were
friends. He believed that they wouldn't
in a million years invade.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> 21st of August, 1968, is when the Prague
Spring was ruthlessly crushed, and
[music]
6,500 tanks and 50,000 troops came in
from Russia and suppressed Dubček's
opening up and now it was firmly under
the iron curtain.
>> Dubček lasted another year until 1969
when he was deposed [music] and he
became an ambassador. Of course, he was
never the same again.
>> Marvin Gaye's I Heard It Through The
Grapevine is the ultimate song of
suspicion, passion and jealousy and
nobody could do it better than Marvin
Gaye.
>> The creativity of black America in those
years
>> [music]
>> when every you know, now we look back
and we talk about psychedelic this and
all the Beatles and the Stones and the
groups and it's all great, but the
things that stand the test of time more
and more
Aretha Otis, Marvin Gaye, Four Tops, you
know, that
those guys, you know.
>> I Heard It Through The Grapevine is
Marvin Gaye actually beginning the next
phase of his musical career in which he
becomes a prophet and which he starts to
say people wake up something's going on
this country. You know, we dance to it
and we hopped around, but actually
[music] the tone of it is about be
careful because something's coming and
it's not a good thing.
>> [music]
>> Towards the end of August, Chicago would
erupt in [music] violence as anti-war
and anti-establishment demonstrations
clashed with police at the Democratic
Convention.
>> [music]
>> The Democratic Convention of 1968,
Robert Kennedy was meant to be there,
but he'd been assassinated. So, you had
Hubert Humphrey and McCarthy and it
became a they became a huge protest
against it.
>> Feelings were already running high.
There had been riots, there'd been lots
of demonstrations and there were some
very
they they the
activists and they said they were going
to do things like disrupt it.
>> At the time, the mayor of Chicago,
Richard Daley, had said, "If you kids
come here with this, I'm dealing with
you. I'm going to take you out." So, he
had actually armed or uber armed the
Chicago Police Department, which had
already been
>> [music]
>> battling
uh the uprisings in the black community
because Dr. King had been murdered just
months before. So, they were tooled up.
Let's put it this way. [music]
>> Meanwhile, in the center of Chicago,
Abbie Hoffman, who was the leader of
[music] the Yippies, had organized what
he called a Festival of Life. And this
was 10,000 people who were gathered in
Lincoln Park and they attempted to sleep
there.
>> The Yippie movement was a kind of very
politicized version of the Hippie
movement. So, it was a it was a
revolutionary wing,
>> [music]
>> essentially.
>> What these demonstrators were saying was
they hadn't got the president they
wanted. They hadn't got Kennedy, but
they wanted change. Things had to be
different and the young of America
wanted something very different to what
their parents [music] had done.
>> Most of the Democratic delegates were
staying at the Conrad Hilton
>> [music]
>> and that's where Abbie Hoffman and the
protesters decided to launch their set
piece demonstration. This was
dealt with by the police with extreme
brutality.
>> [music]
>> The fact that it was so disastrous for
it to be in Chicago
could not have been foreseen
and the changes in society that made it
disastrous were so
radical and so extreme
that they were just boggling the mind.
>> They burst into the Hilton Hotel where a
lot of us were in there working on the
anti-war movement. They had guns. We
were totally unarmed. People would fall
down on the floor [music] to show that
they were non-violent and they just
stepped on you. It was uh pretty
horrible.
>> What? Like [music] daily? I'd never
considered plus the fact that it was
going to be filmed. The television
companies were all there and they showed
this brutality, [music]
this incredible behavior by the police
going out live and this had a profound
effect on American opinion.
>> To a lot of American people watching on
TV, they hadn't seen this in such close
quarters because many riots simply were
not filmed by TV [music] cameras. There
were TV cameras all over the Democratic
convention because they were going there
to film it anyway.
>> [music]
>> So suddenly these journalists who were
expecting to film rather political
conversation were filming these mass
pitched battles.
>> It really did feel
apocalyptic. It was something I followed
avidly, you know, television,
newspapers.
What was going on cuz I had people I
knew there.
>> The Chicago as they came to be known
were all arrested
and after appeals all of them were, you
know, escaped jail but it was very very
close.
>> [music]
>> In September CBS debuted [music]
two shows that would go on to become
television classics.
>> [music]
>> Hawaii Five-O made its debut in
September 1968 and this became [music]
the longest-running police series in
American television history.
>> You know, it's a a good fun cop show but
Hawaii Five-O is all about the music.
Surely.
>> Hawaii Five-O had bad theme song.
[music] First of all, it was
it was a theme song with the woman doing
the hula at the beginning to the theme
song so it was great.
>> I don't think there's ever been better
theme [music] music to a television
program. And of course, this sort of
iconic phrase that ran through the whole
thing that we used to say all the time,
"Book 'em, Danno." Every time uh
he finally got his man, [music] it was
"Book 'em, Danno." So, we were all "Book
'em, Danno."
>> Book 'em, Danno.
>> Jack Lord was kind of um
>> [music]
>> a movie star-ish person on television.
He had the same looks.
He was kind of like [music] Steve
McQueen. And he was just so cool. You
know, Hawaii, most of us grew up in
cities, and there was Hawaii with these
beaches and stuff. So, it was iconic.
>> Good evening.
>> [music]
>> This is 60 Minutes.
>> 60 Minutes was
the dawn of television investigative
journalism. [music]
Essentially, it was a magazine show, but
it featured Vietnam. It featured police
brutality. [music]
And it wasn't from a particularly
left-wing position or anything. It
featured issues [music] of the day. And
this really hadn't been done before.
>> We do think this is sort of a new
approach.
We realize, of course, that new
approaches are not always instantly
accepted. We'll see.
I'm Mike Wallace.
We will, indeed.
>> You know, there are definitely things in
British media and television that are
way ahead of equivalents in America, but
I think that
set a kind of standard. [music]
>> [music]
>> Jose Feliciano was a blind Puerto Rican
guitarist, and he changed Light My Fire
into a lament rather than the rather
swaggering version which The Doors had
done. But the writer of the song, Robbie
Krieger of The Doors, he loved it. He
said he really captured
what it could have been, this song.
>> [music]
>> fire. I used to see Jose Feliciano come
in to the Club 47 [music] in Boston,
folk club there.
His uncle would lead him. You know, he
was blind even then.
>> [music]
>> He was a teenager and he played his
guitar and this incredible voice and
he'd sing these amazing things.
Everybody would be like,
"What was that? Wow."
It's [music] great to hear songs turned
upside down and
done differently and and again, [music]
I
It was It was great in those days. You
could turn on the radio and just hear
great music, you know, it was just at a
flick of a dial.
>> [music]
>> Could you hand me a garment?
[music]
>> All Along the Watchtower is Jimi Hendrix
doing Bob Dylan better than Bob Dylan
could ever do it because Jimi Hendrix is
such a brilliant guitarist and I think a
fantastic singer as well. I mean, he
just he puts so much feeling [music]
into that song. It turns it into
something incredibly exciting.
>> That I have to say is even better of a
re-imagination of a song than Jose
Feliciano Light My Fire.
Jimi Hendrix doing All Along the
Watchtower.
That opening chord on the 12-string and
>> [snorts]
>> genius.
>> I think Jimi Hendrix is held in such
high esteem by other musicians and other
songwriters that people like Dylan were
very, very pleased for for him to be
doing their material.
>> [music]
>> In 1968, the Summer Olympics were held
in October in Mexico City. [music]
In the 200 m, Tommy Smith won the gold
and John Carlos the bronze.
>> At the medal presentation [music]
ceremony, at the very moment these
athletes were anointed as being the best
in the world, the two Americans turned
up bare feet in order to represent the
poverty that they saw around them. They
wore beads, too.
And they each wore a glove.
And as the medals were being presented,
they raised one gloved arm each and
scowled. And this was [music] the black
power salute at the time.
>> It was sensational.
It really embodied everything that we
young people were feeling
>> [music]
>> in that year. It was amazing thing to
do. It was as strong as taking knees
now, but it really made people think
[music] a lot.
>> They are immediately chastised for this
because the Olympics is meant to be
apolitical, that's what they say. And so
they're banned from the Olympic [music]
Village. They are They are very strongly
criticized for this.
>> Initially, the athletic body didn't get
behind them at all [music] and
criticized them and felt that this was
uh the wrong thing to do.
But when they came back,
it was a different matter. They came
back as heroes.
>> Tommy Smith and John Carlos, who will be
remembered as this. And their careers
would forever
be dwarfed by this one moment. But many
years later, they both said that they
had no regrets whatsoever.
>> I think it was Tommy Smith who said that
that you know, if he wins the race, he's
an American, [music] not a black
American. If he does something bad,
they'd call him a negro. He said we're
we're black and we're proud to be black.
>> October was a big month for film with
several classics being released within
days of each other.
And they didn't get much bigger than
Peter
Yates's Bullitt.
>> The thing about Bullitt, first of all,
it was a Steve McQueen picture. The
second thing that it was about was that
everybody wanted a Mustang. Bullitt has
a scene in it that's about, I think, 10
minutes long, 12 minutes long of the
duel of these Well, there's a Mustang in
it.
>> What it it really be remembered for is
the incredible chase scene. And what
they did was that they they filmed it in
streets. Generally, Hollywood movies are
filmed on on lots [music] and sets. And
Bullitt broke that mold. And you know,
you had the the famous chase scene,
which is actually through the streets of
San Francisco.
>> The whole story is about, you know, a
cop and all of these things. [music] But
the iconic moment is the chase. You're
in that car. You're with Steve McQueen.
You don't know how this is going to end.
And it is full on. And it's just gears
and crashing and motors. [music] And it
was just iconic. I kind of boys' movie,
but I saw it, too.
>> You're still afraid.
>> Stop it now. I mean it.
>> They're coming to get you, Barbara.
>> Night of the Living Dead cost $114,000
[music] to make. And it recouped $21
million.
So, it was a a massive success.
>> Night of the Living Dead is the first
countercultural horror movie.
George A. Romero made it on next to
nothing. And it's this film which is
about zombies com- you know, taking
over. And you know, the
the survivors hide out in this
farmhouse.
>> Yeah, it looks like about eight or 10
out there now.
>> There's more than there were.
>> There are a lot out back, too.
>> So far, the best advice they ever gave
me
>> [music]
>> On the surface, it was a horror film. It
was certainly incredibly
brutal. The violence was was shocking.
And but also, it wasn't just a horror
film. Like so much in 1968, [music]
there was stuff going on under the
surface.
>> There are a lot of theories that he was
he was reflecting Vietnam. And he's
reflecting what was going on at the
time. But also, the lead is black, which
is very unusual for a movie like this.
It became a key moment in the
counterculture because you had a you
know, horror movies were traditionally
seen as trashy and silly and fun and
entertaining, but not of cultural
[music] relevance. And suddenly you had
this film which was actually
almost a metaphor or euphemism for what
was going on in the country.
>> [music]
>> In November of 1968, the American
[music] people are suffering what you
can definitely say is identity crisis.
They've seen so much police brutality.
They've seen riots, they've seen
shootings, the shooting of Kennedy, the
shooting of Martin Luther King. They are
beginning to be increasingly scared
about the future. [music] And so there
starts to be this great movement towards
conservative behavior.
>> I will
>> Nixon appealed to what he called the
silent majority. Now, this is the time
of the Vietnam protests, it's the time
of the hippie movement, the student
movement, this flowering of kind of new
consciousness. The silent majority were
all those people all over America who
felt very alienated from this.
>> He promised to boost America's nuclear
capability. And [music]
effectively, he promised to take America
away from the protests and the trauma of
1968.
>> First
priority foreign policy objective of our
next administration
will to be bring an honorable end to the
war in Vietnam.
>> Nixon makes the promise to come out of
Vietnam. And as a consequence,
>> [music]
>> Nixon becomes president. So all this
run-up, all this talk of liberal, this
talk of change, we now have a very
conservative Republican president in
power.
>> [music]
>> Change would also arrive at another of
America's oldest institutions.
>> Yale University, the bastion of
American education
didn't [music] admit women. Now, as
early as 1966,
they had, in fairness to them, tried to
reverse that policy. They tried to link
with Vassar, the female [music] college,
but Vassar were having none of this. So,
in 1968, both Yale and Vassar, [music]
totally separately, agreed to take the
other sex into their college.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Albatross was a British number one for
the
>> [music]
>> Peter Green era of Fleetwood Mac. It
also went to number four in America. And
it was sort of musical [music] balm for
troubled times. It was a beautiful,
slow, languid instrumental with the
sounds [music] of the seashore.
>> Suddenly, you had these very, very long,
beautiful, one might say ponderous
guitar solos by this incredible
guitarist called Peter Green, [music]
who was then leading Fleetwood Mac, and
he would have terrible mental health
problems that would force him to leave,
but at this stage, he was he was turning
Fleetwood Mac, who'd been around for
quite a long time, into this [music] big
blues phenomenon.
>> [music]
>> Once Upon a Time in the West is is a
great film.
>> This is Henry Fonda as the star of this
movie.
>> Sergio Leone, who'd done the the Unknown
Man trilogy with [music] Clint Eastwood,
thought he'd had it with Westerns, but
then he was given the opportunity to
direct Henry Fonda as a villain. So, he
took his chance, did it, and the results
were absolutely brilliant.
>> [music]
>> It had a kind of very very elegant feel
and it changed Westerns. It was almost
like AN EXISTENTIALIST WESTERN.
>> IT WAS A LANDMARK IN every way, every
way. And the theme song was was epic.
>> [music]
[music]
>> On Christmas Eve of 1968, the Apollo 8,
a program that had been begun by
President [music] Kennedy, goes into the
orbit of the moon, it goes round the
moon.
Uh what it gets are these [music]
amazing pictures.
>> The Earth from here is a grand oasis in
the vastness of space.
>> We've never seen Earth like this before.
[music]
So, it was it was a breakthrough not
just in exploration of the moon and
[music] you know, of course it wouldn't
be long before man would land on the
moon,
but also of actually seeing our Earth
from from space.
>> Thank you. Well, looking at ourselves as
seen from 180,000 miles out in space.
>> The crew actually read some Genesis
while they're up there in the shuttle.
Very [music] interesting moment. On one
hand, it is the ultimate representation
of American power. They have sent men
down to the moon taking photos, but also
it shows us how teeny tiny Earth is, how
it's a small place it is. And so, one
hand with the greatest [music] and the
smallest in the universe.
>> After such a year of turmoil, I think
it's quite significant that Time
magazine had as its men of the year the
three-man crew of Apollo 8. These were
incredibly brave men. This was the first
time a manned aircraft had gone out of
the earth's orbit. It's the first time
that anyone had seen the dark side of
the moon.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Once in my life it just makes you love
Stevie Wonder really. He's just so happy
[music]
and there's something about Stevie
Wonder that just lifts you up and for
once in my life is a great example of
that.
>> This is his I call his Broadway song.
[music] Gene Kelly could have sang this
song and that's the genius of it because
Stevie does it and he does [music] it
magnificently.
>> For Once in My Life is a very
optimistic way to close [music]
1968. It was full of light, full of joy
and [music] like Apollo 8 it showed that
1968 need not end with the despair
>> [music]
>> and disappointment and violence that had
characterized the year.
>> [music]
[singing]
[music]